this is Brandon sanderson's how to write
Science Fiction and Fantasy course this
week we are talking about World building
week two and I also spent a little extra
time slipping in a conversation of
viewpoint intense so I think it'll be
very useful to you and we are still
planning a Q&A on character web
exclusive so if you want to get your
questions to me on how to write
characters put them in the comment
section of the Q&A on character that
we've already done with the class we'll
do a web exclusive for you try to watch
that lecture and make sure you're not
repeating the questions hey everybody
Welcome to riding SCI fiction
[Applause]
fantasy I am your trained lecture monkey
Brandon Sanderson um I am mostly over my
cold so that's
good I still can't hear wor beans um
went and saw an ENT today and he's like
oh yeah you got over the cold but
there's stuff trapped still in your ears
so I feel like I'm underwater um but I
can hear like at
40% and so we'll see if how well I can
take questions they have a microphone up
here in case we need to get to that um
but today I want to dig deeper into
sanderson's thirdd law um and really
talk about World building uh and this
idea of World building and service of
story we're going to launch into a
larger World building discussion and
then I want to shave a half hour off the
end of the world building lecture to do
Viewpoint intense um because after this
we have four weeks left next week will
be Q&A on World building then we'll do
two lectures on the business of writing
and then we'll have our final lecture
Q&A on whatever you want to know uh kind
of maybe focus a little bit on business
side and things like that so we've got
kind of the last um writing lecture
today with the Q&A after and then we're
going to launch into the business side
of things um so today
I want to talk about this idea of World
building and why we do it um and how we
you can make it a highlight of your
stories and something to necessarily
hang your story on if you want to people
often ask me what comes first uh a World
building idea is it a character um is it
a plot idea and for me generally I need
to have a couple of good ideas in each
of the are is before I feel like a novel
is coming together and I write primarily
novels I think you can write a good
short story based on one idea most good
novels are an intersection of multiple
ideas um to speak about this for
instance sometimes there'll be ideas
I've had for a while and they'll be
brewing in my brain sometimes they are
things I need to design in order to fit
the story when I was coming up with
misbourne I believe that the first idea
for Mporn was the story of what happens
if the hero failed right uh I think I
told you guys this story reading Harry
Potter and I'm like ah these dark Lords
never get a break what if you know he
won um what what if what if Voldemort
won what if Sauron uh took the ring and
took over um that was an idea that sat
in my brain for a while I never wrote
that book because man what a bummer of a
book
right you know like I'm sure you could
do it well with the right promises but a
book where at the end everyone fails and
saaron takes over you know I I couldn't
find the right take on it um that is
what I would call a plot idea kind of a
plot hook but it also is a setting hook
you can see right like it's a world
where the dark lord won and I took it
from plot hook let's tell a story about
the dark lord winning and moved it to
setting hook what if this is set in a
place place where the dark lord had won
and then what is my story well my love
of heist novels became my new plot hook
I'm going to write um a fantasy story uh
that is a heist um and I was on to
something because soon after that right
around the time I did Mporn right after
we got Liza Lura and um we got the
gisher um and things like six of crows
which are all kind of approaching the
same idea it felt like the market was
ready for heist fantasy and no one had
had yet done it um and so this idea that
became my plot idea other setting ideas
for misbourne came separately alaman as
a magic system had been designed for a
previous book that I had written and it
hadn't turned out very
well and so I repurposed it I always
call it throw the idea into the wood
chipper and break it down to its uh its
its pieces and then rebuild it the
powers in the original vers of mbor were
different I now Had A thieving crew and
this is where we go into World building
and service of story where I said all
right what are the powers that a group
of Thieves would need that could enhance
the different traditional roles of a of
a classic thieving crew you've got your
sneaky one you've got your fast talking
one you've got your heavy let's design
Powers around this
um another idea was the Mist itself and
the Mist came along cuz I was driving to
my mother's house in Idaho Falls I was
passing up through that Northern Port
part of Utah into Idaho anyone who's
done that drive it's right around where
you're almost to to the city Portage um
that has like a gas station and nothing
else and I know that because that's
right where I'm running out of gas so I
always fill up there um I hit a fog bank
at uh you know at at speed on highway
speeds and I'm like wow this looks
really cool it's fading in and out
there's fog and then there's not fog and
I'm like I want to use that in a
story it's kind of odd because one of
the be best writing adages out there
that I believe is uh is a truism is
write what you know you'll hear this
often if you take entry-level courses in
creative writing write what you know and
your response as a fantasy novelist
might be oh great uh write what I know
I'm writing about worlds that don't
exist how can I know uh and my response
to you is dig into why people say write
what you know they say write what you
know because um you want to be able to
lend some authenticity some excitement
to this story and really I take that for
Fantasy novel as saying dig into the
things that interest you that you want
to learn that you see that Fascinate You
or that you are already an expert in dig
into those and find ways to let those
inform your plot and especially your
world building you have Fascinations and
unique mixes of Fascinations and unique
mixes of life experiences that you can
mine just in a mercenary way to write
unique settings and stories that no one
else could write and you can lend that
authenticity even if you're also at the
same time exploring things that you want
to know more about uh as you build your
story I envision um world building when
I sit down to to build my uh World guide
what I generally do is I start with my
three pillars setting plot uh characters
usually setting character plot and I'll
make new headings in Microsoft Word and
I'll be like all right I'm going to
write down all the ideas I've had over
the years as this story has started to
build and grow um it's almost like I
describe it sometimes like all the
individual ideas are like you know atoms
bouncing around and sometimes they slam
into each other and stick together I
know that's not how chemistry actually
works but imagine this molecule being
formed from these UniQue Ideas yeah it
can do that sometimes it you know
creates uh the power by which all life
uh can exist when it does that but it
does that's that's when they hybridize
not when they make a molecule but anyway
um you have all these individual ideas
bouncing around and the book starts to
grow from them like frost growing on uh
a piece of metal they're just expanding
um as these ideas
intersect Miss born the idea of the hero
lost mixed with the idea of what about a
story about a thieving crew made both of
those ideas better for me more exciting
I don't think there's a generically kind
of um objective better when it comes to
ideas but for me I'm like I didn't want
to write this book it was a downer but
if that's the world that these
characters live in that they can respond
against and then you're pulling a heist
and who better to Heist than the dark
lord who won suddenly both ideas were
more interesting to me that's what I'm
looking for and I start writing those
down setting character plot everything
that I've had for this book there will
be plenty of holes at that point I will
go to my notes file which is this day on
my phone I store in
Gmail um you know I downloaded a bunch
of notes programs and I never used them
I just found that if I make a new draft
in Gmail that I know exactly where it is
and I can get it on all my devices and
Gmail became my notes
program kind of silly but that's where
it is and so the file now it used to be
named cool stuff that needs to be used
sometime that's when was on my computer
now it's just called new notes
original but you got to be able to find
it easily so um and I go to that and I'm
like are there ideas I've had in the
past that when I combine it with the
things on here make the ideas more
interesting but I'm always focused on
that idea of sanderson's Third Law it's
not about density of ideas it's about
how the ideas influence each other and
the depth that you can kind of play with
those ideas um the the World building of
the hero having failed led me into kind
of taking a apart the classic Epic
Fantasy and saying all right let's deal
with prophecy let's deal with chosen
ones let's deal with dark Lords and
let's deconstruct all three of those
ideas and write a book about each right
the first one's about you know the idea
of the dark lord the second one's about
uh kind of the um the idea of Prophecy
and the third one's about the idea of
the chosen one though they're all kind
of about all three ideas and really
trying to deconstruct this um and do
something new with it and that idea just
had a lot of depth to it you could see
how I can approach the idea of the Dark
Lord one from three different places it
informed who seed become became and it
informed who Vin became it informed uh
who Ellen and kelsier were all about
these ideas and so that's what I'm
looking for and that's what I mean by
sanderson's thirdd law this idea of Let
Your World building go deeper explore
what you have ask yourself the
ramifications brainstorming sessions
with writing groups can be really handy
for this uh they will give you a lot you
can't use but they might uh send you in
directions that you can and then I split
my world building into
generally three different
portions um I'm going to talk about it
kind of as two portions now but usually
for me in my document so maybe I should
revise this lecture I have what we call
physical setting
I have
cultural and because it's a thing for me
I put
magic in its own setting um its own
section I mean the idea being what's the
magic system going to be it is part of
both the physical and cultural setting
um but I kind of start here physical
setting for me this is all the stuff
that would still exist in the world if
Sapient beings weren't there messing
with it right
um cultural setting is all the stuff
that Sapient beings create um all the
all the World building that has to do
with the ways people think and interact
and things like this and the magic is
what is my magic system right how what
is this intersection it's a big enough
bullet point for me that I make it U on
its own we talked about magic at length
last week maybe too much um and so we're
going to focus a little bit on these
two and what I usually like to do here
is I like to dig in and show you just
how much stuff there is that you could
maybe do in a fantasy novel right those
who have been in the class before you
you know what this process is we're just
we're not going to spend forever at it
uh and we'll see let not yell them out
that's raiseed hands because of my ears
um but let's start talking about some of
the great things you can you can
brainstorm if you're going to come up
with some physical setting atams for
your world building Canyons okay
topography yep what else weather weather
viruses viruses
yeah um and I would say
disease geology G
geology sorry okay let's raise hands
really I I I have to focus and see
what's that okay flora and
fauna
um let's take a deeper dive into these
like what kinds of things can you ask
yourselves about the Flora and
Fauna food chain food chain exactly um
anything else you can think of you can
ask yourself about those what what
animals are domesticated yes well that
would be that's right in this middle
ground but you're right kind of
domestication
I'd say that Strays a little bit in the
cultural but a little phys physical
that's great what weather can they
survive in yeah yeah what's what what
are the biomes um and what lives in what
biome right those are arrows pointing at
the biomes what else do we got
adaptations adaptations how have these
creatures evolved to this specific
setting and to these biomes so yeah
adaptation
you see me doing a ton of that in
Stormlight right natural disasters oh
yeah natural
disaster yeah you'll see my handwriting
get worse and worse as we go um uh the
the astronomy of the area okay yeah yeah
astronomy what would we call that Co
cosmology um the right because cosmology
that gets into like mythology though
doesn't it well no cosmology where are
the where where are the where are my
scientist you'd say you'd say it's like
the makeup yeah makeup we'll just call
it
cosmology we'll just use that but
pretend cosmology doesn't involve any of
the mythology U mythologizing of the
cosmology like the you know I'm not sure
if that word includes the idea of some
mythology in it or not not sure um so
yeah how fast planet rotates oh yeah
yeah yeah um
rotation um and someone said geography
we'll put geography
uh but rotation title
lock right you can get like forever like
I don't want to go on this too much but
the idea that we could probably take
flora and fauna and we could spend
probably an hour talking about the
various things that you could come up
with for unique and interesting ways uh
for your Flor and fauna to exist um like
you know Speaker for the Dead
just it's one of the best parts of the
world building in that book is how he
approaches the the interaction between
flora and fauna and it's so fascinating
and science fiction fantasy is so good
at saying yeah this doesn't exist on
Earth but we can do it in our books and
we can look at the ramifications of what
would happen if you have unique biology
to alien species um cultural setting oh
boy yeah um anything to do with
technology okay tech
level yeah and even tech level
disparities between different cultures
yeah religion
religion yep food food food lore
um my uh my my um thesis chair well when
I was in undergrad so my my um what do
you call it honors thesis chair was Dr
Thurby BYU food lore was her specialty
um and so it was a lot of fun to talk to
her about food lore and how how it could
relate to fantasy novels and things like
that so yeah interactions what do you
mean by interactions social moras yeah
social
yeah uh I always talk about um how you
know in rashar there's the safe hand
right that started because in Korea I
asked I sat with my leg up and showed
the bottom of my foot to my companion
who was Korean he was like oh no that's
a dire insult I'm like the bottom of my
foot's a dire insult he's like yes dire
insult never do that uh and it turns out
it's true don't show the bottom of your
foot to people um was just so
fascinating to me that it wasn't um like
it was a taboo in a different way that I
hadn't ever experienced I'm like wow I
need to open my mind to the different
kinds of tabos that can exist yeah
systems of Law and government yeah law
and government
how how does that work right yeah back
here um languages and dialects languages
and dialects we're going to erase magic
for
now and
dialects you can totally read that right
oh I already asked you for what we're
gonna go right here no I didn't okay
both of you can
talk wait you said you weren't going to
talk before class during the 4 that's
right all right the time is lapsed go
ahead um social like social roles such
as gender roles and class roles gender
and class roles
yep yeah fantasy and science fiction
never delves into that relationship to
the Natural World okay
yeah ship to woo that stuff okay over
here Traditions Traditions
yeah that's one that I don't think
enough fantasy digs into that is a
really big part of a lot of people's
lives here and then over there
Educational Systems education yeah has
there
apprenticeship um is there formalized
school how do people learn things
fashion fashion
yep a man after adelyn's
Hearts building techniques and material
to building techniques material yeah um
all right we're going to do one more
right here festivals and celebrations
festivals and celebrations sorry to all
those who rais your hands in the back
they had awesome suggestions too
um um okay what is the purpose of this
why do we spend like 10 minutes on this
um that's overwhelming and we spent 10
minutes on it we could spend hours on it
in fact particularly in cultural setting
I bet we could take some of these like
for instance language and
dialects Grandpa tolken spent how many
years on languages and dialects for his
series years maybe decades on just one
point on the board right um and like you
could do that you
could give yourself World Builder
disease we talked about World Builder
disease I don't think we have uh World
Builder disease is something that uh
that I coined uh among one of my early
writing group where we talked about the
idea that you could spend so long on
this that you get paralized by the
amount that you have to do and because
each of these elements is a rabbit hole
that you could spend months or years on
that when you start on one you realize
how much left there is to World bu and
you get daunted by it and you never
actually
write this may have happened to you it
may have happened to your friends I have
uh friends that I know who are like I
can't write yet because I haven't
finished like I don't know what the food
lore of my Society is food lore is
enormously important how can I write my
book until I know the food lore um right
like this sort of
thing can paralyze you yeah has that
ever been you has what have you ever
been under that have I ever been under
this I have generally had uh good
deadlines so um I don't know if I don't
think I've talked about this in class
before but I talk about it often my
secret if you want to dig deep why is
Brandon as successful as he is I blame
being an artist raised by an
accountant and if you see in my books
accountants showing up now and then it's
CU my mom an accountant um she was the
one of the head accountants for the city
of Idaho Falls I grew up in Nebraska uh
she did other things in Nebraska other
accounting stuff and things but she
graduated from BYU uh first in her class
when she was one of the only women in
her accounting classes um and so my mom
your accountant over here yeah oh just
aad Mom yeah yeah praise to the mom um
and um she deserves it
right my mom would say she's not very
creative I think that is um a
misapplication of the word creativity I
think everything that human beings do
requires immense creativity I think
being a parent requires so much
creativity uh if you've ever had to
entertain a four-year-old you know what
I'm talking about right um but every job
if you don't think it's creative to
figure out systems for accounting when
the systems current systems aren't
working which she would all often do
then I think you misunderstand the
definition creative but she was raised
in an era where you were either a
creative person or you were not you were
left brained or right brained right um I
see you know the last 20 years people
talking less about that because it is a
false dichotomy um but I think I do lean
naturally toward the Whimsy the head in
the clouds and all of these things uh I
love World building I love planning I
hate revisions right this is a very
natural sort of um I could have been the
person who spent years planning because
that's so much fun um but when I got
back from my mission and I realized I
wanted really to be a novelist um and
every other novelist out there who
person who wanted to be a novelist had
been spending 10 15 20 years working on
their books they're 5-year-olds who you
know who are writing stories um and I
realized I needed to put into place some
of these structures my uh mom had taught
me about how to be successful and so I
would give myself deadlines I would say
I'm allowed to World build for this
amount of time and then I need to move
on to the book and that was really
helpful for me because what I soon
discovered is I don't particularly early
in my career I didn't generally know
where I needed to put my world building
effort because back then I didn't know
how to outline I didn't have the
structure I do now now I can kind of
know but back then it was as the story
developed I realized oh I Should Have
Spent My World building time on this
like when I wrote my very first book
white sand I spent a t ton of time on
the languages because that's what
Grandpa tolken did and then I never used
it because that wasn't relevant everyone
was speaking the same language it was a
murder mystery taking place in one city
cuz that's kind of where I gravitate
instead of the quest fantasy the kind of
social dynamics um of people in an urban
environment uh in Epic Fantasy and I
barely used the language I'd throw it in
for fun because I did all this work on
it right what should I have figured out
what their justice system looks like
it's a murder mystery that's really
important right um spent no time on that
early on like it was all on what is the
what does the planet look like and
things like that what is the magic
system but on some of the things that
were really relevant and I found that as
I started writing I would find those
things and then I trained myself to be
like all right I'm either going to go do
it now or I'm going to put a placeholder
in depending on how vital it is um one
of the things I want to talk about is
this idea
that because this is so
paralyzing what you generally want to do
is you want to pick a few of these
things and as a new writer pick ones
that you already have some expertise in
in some way and then maybe some things
that you want to learn go read some
books on and study but the danger is if
you spend so much time Ro building you
will end up doing what I wanted to do
which is shove a bunch of linguistics
into your book because you spend all
that time on it when it doesn't actually
match your book um let's talk about the
iceberg
so fancy I feel like it's so fancy even
though this is like technology that's
exist for you know 80 years but it feels
so fancy it's such an upgrade for my
other room um the iceberg people often
talk about the World
building of a fantasy novel as best
being described using the old Iceberg
metaphor that you all know right um You
have to be careful because this stuff
that's underneath the waves if you start
putting too much of that in your book
starts reading like an encyclopedia
entry and this is the dreaded info dump
right the idea being
that if you start your paragraphs start
reading like their boring entries in a
dictionary you're going to lose your
reader and you're going to have a lot of
problems but you still want them to feel
like all of that information is there um
that's what evokes the sense that
they're in an actual world the trick I
think to being a successful fantasy and
science fiction novelist in today's um
environment is to actually have a hollow
Iceberg what I mean by this is this is
the stuff that you legitimately know you
have done your research you have spent
the
time this is the stuff that informs who
your characters are the decisions
they'll be making um and whatnot this is
super relevant and I would recommend you
do it at some part in the process you
can frontload you can write your book
decide what you need go do your world
building and then come back and put it
in either one is totally fine you can
stop in the middle and do it as long as
you consistently go back to your story
and don't then get into World Builder
disease and start saying well I did pick
food lore but that relates to social Mor
which oh no that relates to building
materials because what can they get
which oh no now I need to know their
architecture and then I need to know
their tech level
right be careful about that um the rest
of this you want to evoke a sense that
it is there but you don't want to do all
that uh upfront I recommend against it
unless you really really like it that's
fine once again you can spend 20 years
on a book if you want to um you you use
these tools how you want but what I
recommend for these is if you do this
very well and people trust you on the
things that you have done very well they
will expect a line or two about the
other things that have some sort of
light story hook to them um that they're
like oh someday I want to hear about
that which gives you seeds to use in
future
books um or they will also accept if in
some books you do all this work and then
the rest of this you kind of just rely
on what people already know the and a
lot of uh stories science fiction in
particular you know they're they're not
going to spend a lot of time explaining
to you what FTL
is because everybody who's reading a
science fiction book knows all right in
science fiction books you can f travel
faster than speed of light and in some
books it's like we Wormhole from here to
here and there are jump Gates and they
leave it at that
you they don't explain how or why
because it's not part of what the story
is specifically about you rely on the
fact that people understand what that is
you rely on the fact that people know
what a dragon is you don't explain how
dragons can fly in your world even
though the mass to uh Wing ratio should
not allow it you just let people accept
that they're dragons um and you you let
it go right um and these are the sorts
of things that sometimes you want to do
uh Dan Wells um my writer friend is is a
really great master of a tool to help
with this he often recommends when you
describe a
room or a setting describing one thing
in really high
detail and letting that evoke the rest
uh the classic example he'll use is he's
like you walk in a room and you describe
well the bullet holes in the front
window and that the light is flickering
and that the ceiling fan doesn't work
people fill in the holes to be like okay
this is you know a room that's not taken
care of you're probably in the slums
they will fill in the dust they will
fill in that the the door probably
squeaks they will do these so rather
than a paragraph like this you put a
paragraph like this and hope you can
evoke the rest that doesn't mean that
paragraphs like this aren't useful and
some writers really like them um but if
you are putting paragraphs description
like this make sure they sing and you
are really good at it is what I would
recommend yeah so with with this in mind
how often should you include something
in your story and then have your
solution or answer being to it well it's
a fantasy story so I can do what I want
to do uh it really depends on the type
of fantasy story you're telling how hard
and soft your magic systems are whether
you're going to get into it like for
instance if it's not going to be plot
relevant for instance the jump Gates
whether the jump gates work or not if
those are not relevant to your story all
that's relevant is that we can get from
this planet to this planet then you
don't need to explain you say it's a
science fiction story they have jumpgate
technology let's move on to what our
story is actually about and let people
accept it uh people will swallow things
like that and sometimes by opening the
can of worms of explaining it if it's
not plot relevant then this gets you
into the trouble of number one they're
going to want to know
more number two you might start boring
people so half your audience will want
to know more and half your audience will
be bored and you end up with with all
this stuff that isn't story
relevant you may want that in your story
there are valid reasons to want that um
Lord of the Rings is not a bad story for
wanting to spend time um on the the
songs but it depends on your personal
goals and as I said we're pretending
that you want to make a living writing
science fiction fantasy which is
generally going to mean a book a year so
you've got limited time for this um
so dig into the things that you are
passionate about and start there make
them relevant to your characters in some
way if you are really fascinated in the
differences between religions have that
plot and character relevant make
character decisions informed by who they
are and their religious choices make
things harder and easier depending on
you know don't just have it there spend
your time worldbuilding the things that
are going to influence the decisions
your characters make and the challenges
they face is my kind of General
recommendation uh that encompasses
this let's talk just a little bit about
uh the Pyramid of abstraction uh and
then we'll do some questions on this and
maybe dig into it a little bit more
pyramid of distraction so this is um
this is how I like to talk about
grounding a
scene we got a problem in fantasy novels
in that we like to deal with very
abstract
topics all writing does right um at the
same time the whole book is an
abstraction and beyond that no rule or
law of our world can be taken for
granted in your fantasy world this
presents a unique challenge to the
writer of a fantasy novel my mentor Dave
uh Wolverton uh introduced this once by
saying he once wrote uh in a manuscript
early in a book he flew across the room
to mean he went across he jump you know
ran across the room really fast because
he'd been writing some contemporary
things and his editor said can the
character actually fly or not and Dave
realized oh this is the opening of a
fantasy novel my character could be
flying using metaphoric language is kind
of dangerous in that situation I've
always remembered that introduction um I
learned this thing called The Pyramid
distraction um from another student in
my graduate program um where he taught
it to me and if you've seen me do this
before uh stay quiet for now um I kind
of want to lead you through the
experience I had and he said everything
you're going to describe in your book
some of it's going to be concrete and
you want to have a foundation of of
concrete ideas to earn the abstractions
that you're going to be using in your
story and he said let me give you a few
things and you tell me where between
concrete and Abstract this concept might
lie right and so he started me said love
where is
love abstract abstract would you put it
like up here at the top where yeah yeah
okay where would you put a
dogr concrete you'd put a dog down here
okay that's exactly what I did let's
talk about
this if I say dog how many people in
this room imagine the same
dog zero probably right we all have a
different image of a dog in our head if
I say love how many people in here know
what love is and how it actually feels
and how similar will that be to how
other people
feel pretty similar in general we do
have our different things actually love
is more concrete and a dog is more
abstract when it comes to writing a
novel this is hard for us to grasp
because we thought of love as an
abstract thing because you can't hold it
but when you're describing it in a book
it's easier well they both can be
described you say a dog someone's
they're going to picture a dog but
that's an abstract concept to them we're
getting into very kind of platonic sort
of things you know you know what is a
dog and whatnot um and what he said is
you can pull things down on the period
of abstraction by using words
if I
describe a small
wet um you know doah Hunt is that how
you say it doc doc no doc weener
dog my Grandma had one what do you how
do you say it do doc doc I can't hear
why am I asking for your help I can't
even hear I'm gonna say h a poodle I can
say poodle a small wet
poodle in the rain huddled in an
Alleyway whimpering and watching the
people walk by hoping that one of them
will stop and give it some comfort you
now are picturing about the same dog
right maybe not 100% but I have pulled
that concept down on the Pyramid of
abstraction right um
and the idea is that you can almost
always use words to do that to pull
things things down but then your story
gets longer and there's a push and a
pull between how much is too much
becoming an info dump or lingering
outside the character you know and how
much do you want inside the character
the most uh abstract things that um that
we want to put in the book are the
things we call Naval
gazing these things get pulled up on the
um the pyam distraction love we
understand but a character ruminate
on their love will help you understand
them but it'll start to pull you off the
page you'll start to see a white room
rather than a story and it'll stray into
the author telling you things rather
than characters experiencing things and
so the idea is that you pull things down
on the pyramid abstraction to earn the
actual abstract things you want which is
spending time in the character's heads
or explaining magic systems to a world
that doesn't exist or things like this
and that is where you want to spend your
abstraction points sometimes you need to
just say it's a dog sometimes that image
isn't relevant to you and you don't
worry about it I'm not saying everything
needs a thousand modifiers what I am
saying is when you set a
scene anchoring Us in that scene
thinking of the pyramid
abstraction making us feel what the
characters feel hear what the characters
feel using more senses than just site
you will cement the scene for someone
and then when it goes into the character
thinking about you know oh do I do I do
this or do I not the naval gazing as we
call it looking inward you slowly are
drifting upward but the reader stays in
the scene and often times you want to
decide how often you're going to Anchor
people how you're going to Anchor them
in the scene and things like that um
often I like to have big stretches of
dialogue with an anchor at the beginning
occasional beats through the middle a
beat is where a character does something
but not too many beats leaving as much
to the dialogue as I can and then
anchoring at the end of the dialogue so
the dialogue you know quote unquote
speaks for itself that is the style that
I prefer uh that is not a style that
everyone has to use um but it works very
well for me does that become
subconscious as you're as you practice
it or always in the no it really become
subconscious as you're going you'll get
a sense for oh man we're getting out of
scene we're getting out of viewpoint and
right my writing group is pretty good at
this because this is something you know
it'll be like I feel like I lost
Viewpoint I feel like you know we've
been talking so much about this plan to
pull off a heist I forget is this Vin's
Viewpoint is it Kel's Viewpoint and are
they still in the room you know stuff
like that but the more you write the
more you'll be like I need to keep
grounding people in the character in the
scene you want it to be the character
thinking about their plan not just you
presenting the piece from the outline
for the reader to have in their back
pocket um and you you use character and
you use the pyramid abstraction to
Anchor that all right this is how you
start to get this world building across
you think of those anchoring scenes the
thing you're going to describe if you
can
describe an aspect not how the magic
works but the visuals of the magic or of
the interesting setting if you can feel
what it's like to get the sand between
your teeth and in your eyes on a racus
and see the Shimmer of the spice as the
wind blows it then you're on oracus and
you're pulled into this concrete sense
of being there and then when it talks
about prophecy and and and you know Paul
is struggling with if he wants to follow
prophecy because he knows it's not
actually legit but there might be a
legit one too then you're still on a
racus because you've had this you can
see the spice too many times from new
Authors I can't see the spice they
describe their cool magic system but I
can't see the spice shimmering in the
air As the Wind Blows the sand and I
can't feel the heat beating upon me and
feel how much I want to drink that's
what will make it a book instead of a
dictionary and that's what I recommend
you learn to do and that is so much more
important than the giant paragraph on
the cosmology of your world you know how
the gods made it way more important is
what it feels like to be in that chapel
and hear and um you know participate not
just here participate in whatever
rituals and be part of it um and that's
how you you do this in a way that
doesn't feel this is what I call the
Grand skill of writing science fiction
fantasy that doesn't feel like you are
in ding it feels like a character is in
a scene and you're there with them and
that's what I want you to take away from
this world building is there's so much
you can do you can't do it all pick a
couple of things that together make your
story more interesting and make each
other more interesting then devise
scenes to concretely pull us in so we
see the
spice shimmering and we know what this
feels and looks like and let that launch
your fantasy story rather than something
more abstract like Once Upon a Time the
gods did this um used to be that's how
you started a fantasy novel um back in
the 80s every one of them started with a
long prologue about the gods I'm
exaggerating but there were a ton of
those and there they're they don't pull
you into the story they don't give you
characters they don't give you a scene
um that feels like reading Isaiah
um I mean we all love Isaiah right but
feels like reading the s melan um we all
love the sil melan too but you know what
I mean Sil melan is what you read after
you love the Lord of the Rings right
tolken fan are you are a tolken fan no
who was it there was some there's
someone who corrected me on my tolken
yeah there's my tolken fan okay yeah so
there's only
one yeah there's there might be multiple
I might be in real trouble I might get
my my Mayar and my uh Salvador dollies
mixed up I don't know I know are now
because everyone talks about it I don't
know the rest of them um so all right um
questions on that we can do like a
couple questions then I want to do
Viewpoint in tense okay we will do a
whole week on World building next week
so you can uh questions so let's do one
here and then we'll do one more and then
we'll save the rest of them for next
week so we'll do you two and then we're
going to do Viewpoint intense so when we
were talking about characters you said
the worst thing a character can do is
stand in the way of plot yeah would you
say that same thing applies with World
building yes
absolutely now don't get me wrong when I
say worst it's a tool you can use with
but if your main character is
interfering with the story progressing
or some World building element is
slowing down what we want to read you've
got problems and sometimes you need to
do it anyway sometimes that's the
spinach that the reader needs to eat but
you want to make sure that you're not
dumping it all on them at once and
you're splitting it up and you're making
it fun and interesting and when you can
weaving it into the stuff they want to
see if they're there for a romance make
sure that you're doing one of a couple
things either the World building is
super relevant to getting to know the
other person or it's done kind of uh
more
sparely um sparsely I shall say uh and
you're just going to let it be there and
you don't have to dig too much into it
because people are there for the romance
now do understand people come to books
for different reasons you can have a
fantastic romance in a book that has a
ton of World building you just got to
make sure that World building isn't
standing in the way and that your
romance scenes are able to do their
romance really well and that your world
building scenes are interesting for
their own reason and do understand
people read for different reasons if
you're writing a giant epic fantasy book
you're going to have viewpoints that
some readers will like more and other
viewpoints that other readers like more
and they will pick favorites uh and I
think talked about this before and some
people really want the Deep World
building where navani discovers the
nature of sound and investure and other
people don't really want that um and
that's okay um the bigger your book The
more
divisive pieces of it will be but
understand Peter my uh editorial VP says
make sure every chapter in your book has
a chance to be someone's favorite
chapter
and that's been really good advice for
me is why would this specific chapter be
someone's and doesn't have to be
everyone's but why would it be someone's
favorite chapter so when it comes to
World building how do you come up with
names for things and people in the world
naming I'm G to give you the quick
answer for this um I got three tools for
you quick you I couldn't hear you can
make all sorts of peanut gallery
comments about me and I can't get you
back for them enjoy this until the
antibiotics clear up my that one's
already done until the the steroid
sprays open the tubes in my ears as the
anent said will happen when I start uh
snuffing them um
legally all right so naming things three
different ways um the easiest
way uh that also risk some danger so
I'll warn you of the danger is to get
yourself an
atlas pick a region in the world look at
those words and try to devise words that
are somewhat matching this is best if
it's a region that you have some
familiarity with already and that
matches the cultural identity of the
characters you're writing about right
the so when I was when I was working on
uh mistborn I'm like I'm going to use
French inspired names I took French in
high school I have French in my ancestry
um I'm going to I think I can safely go
to France and just pick a region and I
can be like all right this word I'm
going to play with this until it works
really well and it's cool it's the
probably the easiest way one of the
dangers is you might accidentally create
words in that language I didn't know
Ellen was an actual word in
German I was just using Germanic um
Germanic uh kind of sounds in order to
create his name because L is from the
dramatic area um and things like that um
one other danger you can do in this is
you so where fantasy comes there is
conversation to be had about what you're
taking from which cultures and how
you're using it right and I do not think
that the conversation is finished in
this and I don't think there are uh
complete
answers um but I do think
as an author writing fantasy um that the
entire kind of cultural heritage of the
earth is is something that is open as an
option to you but there are risks
Associated um for instance I try to stay
away from using too much Native American
in mind uh that is because my specific
culture has had has had a fraught
history shall we say of you know partial
genocide of a people and it feels like
if I then went and took these things
that it would feel wrong to me um I have
no problem reaching to Korea or Japan
part of this is because I've lived in
Korea but part of it is because both of
these cultures are exporting their
entertainment to me um and offering it
up right you K dramas are now kind of
part of the general cultural um
Zeitgeist um as our Japanese video games
um when I'm looking to um a culture I
also try to be very specific like I can
go with French inspired names no problem
but when I was um going to RAR I'm like
I'm going to pick a specific Dynasty in
Chinese history and I'm going to start
using that because instead of then
conflating entire cultures as a uh
monolith I can be like this is the
dynasty um I had had uh I always forget
it's a dynasty where um where the the
Mongols took over China um and the idea
of this idea of Warlords taking over and
having to learn to be bureaucrats was a
seed idea so I'm going to use that and
then I'm going to reach to some of those
ideas and things like that and even in
some of my naming now and then um but
you know you want to be careful and you
want to um to watch for pitfalls and I
can't get into them all right here I
said this would be brief so that's one
way another way is to become a kind of
student of linguistics and learn what
makes languages uh and why certain
languages work and a few books on
Linguistics will get you most of the way
there where you can say this language is
going to be using this kind of um of
nuance like for instance I think I
mentioned you before why you know why do
I like uh using uh Hawaiian for the horn
eaters it's a really fascinating
language because they have fewer sounds
so the words have to be really long in
order to be unique I find that really
cool um I researched here's why it is
and what happens with why so I use that
as a basis because that actual aspect of
the language was fun to me um and
learning about what aspects of different
languages learning how different
languages you know use conjugation stuff
you can come up with cool things you
don't have to be Grandpa tolken to have
a cool naming system and then the last
one is just pick a linguistic trick I've
done this one a lot symmetrical names
are holy well let's make names that are
symmetrical repeated consonant sounds at
the beginning of
names those are ways to do it these all
are just about a Vibe does it feel right
um I can't go too much more into this is
it quick it's quick yeah do you have
Rock's name memorized uh
I huku makak Al lunam more I think I get
one of the a a alamore I get one of the
things um wrong in there yeah how do you
when you create a how do you check to
make sure it's not something that
already exists yeah Google be sure to
Google your names I'll just say that I
haven't run a foul this too much but you
can't you know you got to watch out
sometimes you will accidentally make
like a
slur or a swear word or things like that
just just you know be
careful have have readers who can can
read and um you know who can warn you
about these things and then have readers
who can to read yeah you're laughing at
that uh I just thought about what I said
um have readers who can read closely and
maybe are familiar with the linguistic
uh region that you're writing
from all right Viewpoint intents one of
the main ways you're going to present
your story to readers is through a
certain View point in a certain tense
what do I mean by this well we're
talking about the stuff from high school
but we're going to dig into it deeper
we're talking about third person first
person and second person all right so we
got third person we got first and we got
second right these are our Viewpoint
meth uh Styles we also have tense past
tense present tense future tense um
so you're going to choose between
past
present
present that's what that says and
future you are almost never going to use
this one and you're almost never going
to use this one unless you want to win a
Hugo
award uh actually fifth season is
fantastic and it does second person
really well if you want to see how to do
second person very well uh Nora
Jameson's fifth season is is an
excellent example of that uh and there's
plenty of future tense things out there
they read really
experimental what I'll say about present
and past is in adult science fiction
fantasy past tense is generally the rule
of thumb present is fine but looks a
little out of place and in contemporary
ya present tense is the rule of thumb
past reads just as well um I I would say
that they default to this so like sci-fi
fantasy I'd say is like 80 to 90% past
tense and 20 to 10% present and ya I've
seen is more like 60 to 70% present
tense maybe 40 to 30% past
tense um and there are different kinds
of um past tense and things but really
we'll dig into that in the viewpoints
right because this is the big
decision because each each of these has
certain nuances to them and certain ways
of doing it so I'm going to erase these
for right now because third has its own
Branch off right you have third
limited and third
omnicient okay so the thing about that
is these also have
branches right third limited uh is
generally the standard rule of thumb uh
third limited is where you are in one
person's head for a given scene and you
will line break or chapter break if
you're going to be in someone else's
head and as soon as you establish
Viewpoint you stick with it through the
rest of the chapter where there's some
Nuance to limited is a lot of writers
like to start an omniscient for a
paragraph or two and ease and delimited
and then stay there usually to the end
of the chapter sometimes s like one or
two paragraphs before the end they phase
back out into an omniscient uh if you
like Robert Jordan if you read him this
is what he would do often particularly
the beginning of the books the wind
scene is in omniscient the wind is
flying through and seeing the world and
then it settles on a character and
you're limited uh for the rest of that
chapter and you'll see other people uh
doing this omniscient has its own
branches where there's white I call true
omniscient um and then there's like um
Storyteller
omniscient so true omniscient is the the
classic example is Dune uh Dune uses
omnicient by saying uh every paragraph
is a different Viewpoint and I won't
generally change heads that I'm in in a
paragraph but any new paragraph can be
in a different Viewpoint and indeed The
Narrative itself is not in any Viewpoint
it is being told by some omniscient
impartial Observer who's describing
what's happening to
you Storyteller omniscient is generally
this sort of hybrid first person third
person where you have some Storyteller
who's gathered the full story and is now
telling it to you piece by piece The
Hobbit is a classic example of this but
if you read Tres in the emerald sea uh
Trust of the emerald C it is also in
Storyteller omniscient Hoy can know
anything that I need him to know and can
tell you anything that I need him to
tell you he is an omniscient for
purposes of this narrative he's not
actually omnicient stories but for the
narrative an omnicient Storyteller who
is occasionally pretending to be limited
but he can switch heads whenever he
wants to and he maintains it kind of in
his storyteller's narrative instead the
alcatra books were also written in this
uh sort of format um and we'll talk
about strength and weaknesses of these
in a second first has a bunch of
different branches as well um over here
is what we call a
pistol uh a pistol first person um
is a um if you've read Dracula it's
Dracula epistolary is found footage
novel um alumina uh which got a lot of
uh Buzz um maybe eight years ago uh in
ya was written like this it is all
redacted documents and texts and things
like that so uh Dracula if you haven't
read it it's found footage it's all
letters and um and people's journals and
things like that telling a story uh very
interesting way to tell a story it's
called epistolary because an epistle so
all told through
letters um we have what I would call
true or
close maybe intimate
um uh uh first person this is the vast
majority of current ya this is a first
person where someone is not telling you
the
story but it's narrated as if in their
head it's almost like you have a chip
that's in their brain that is projecting
to you everything that they're
experiencing as they experience it but
no one is telling you the story The
Character isn't aware that they're a
Storyteller it is basically third
Limited done in the first person and
then the last one of these is indeed the
kind
of the same sort of hybrid that we have
here with this one where a person is
writing their story after the fact this
is actually what Alcatraz is I guess um
and these two kind of blend together you
could say that the hobbit's this but he
pretends to be anti he doesn't use I and
The Hobbit um Bilbo doesn't and so the
idea here is that
when you're someone after the fact
writing their story down um if you've
read um Assassin's Apprentice that is
this um name of the wind is this um but
with a third limited um frame story um
so basically uh it is what you kind of
classically assume as first person when
I was a young man blah blah blah okay so
these are kind of your main tools and
they do
different things which is why it's
important to talk about them you
probably were taught most of this in
school but what they don't talk about is
some of these distinctions and why you
might use one versus another the main
distinction I find between third and
first person is that third is way better
at large
casts this is because you either have an
omniscient narrator smoothing everything
together and giving you basically one
perspective perspective that splits into
many to hold to give kind of thematic
cohesion and narrative cohesion or you
know you're in one person's Viewpoint at
a time and it is constantly repeting
their name rather than I and cementing
in your head who they are and what their
motives are in things like this
generally first person is really strong
for one or two
viewpoints um this is why I think it's
become the standard in ya if you're
going to pick up a ya novel right now
it'll most likely statistically be first
person in the true SL intimate first p
uh first person and it'll be present
tense if you're going to pick up a
fantasy um novel and it from the uh from
the fantasy section it's almost
certainly going to be third Limited in
past tense uh and these are just these
are just because of traditions right
like third Limited
became this default I would say probably
because of people like Robert Jordan
doing a really good job with it I mean
it was settling into it before but it's
kind of weird you can watch if you read
the old books like for instance Enders
Game um Enders Game slips into into Bean
Viewpoint randomly at one part at the
end of a chapter uh because these whole
things hadn't really been settled on yet
and people weren't paying attention to
is this third limited is it what what
are redirect expectations now readers
have different expectations the first
recluse novel by Lee modit uh halfway
through goes from like past tense to
present tense for no good reason and
I've asked him he's like he doesn't even
remember why it just did it was not a
stylistic
choice however you can use contrast for
stylistic choices uh Elizabeth Moon
speed of dark which is about a science
fiction novel I may have mentioned it
before where a cure to autism is
discovered in the future and it's about
an autistic man who's trying decide if
he takes this quote unquote cure because
basically it will transform into a
completely different person and do you
take a cure for something that you're
not sure is a disease or not um and uh
this was written back you know when that
was a novel idea I think generally right
now the discourse has gone that
direction of autism is a different way
of thinking rather than uh than a
disease but back then uh she won the the
nebula award for it it's fantastic book
and in order to contrast
viewpoints uh his Viewpoint is in
present tense and everyone else's
Viewpoint is in past tense and this just
helps you when you transition to his
Viewpoint to be like skip a beat and be
like okay we're seeing Through The Eyes
to someone who processes the world
differently um and or maybe we all
process the world differently but it's
least contrasting um the the differences
between the viewpoints so you can switch
I would say honestly truthfully the
difference between present and past is
negligible except for reader preference
and you may prefer one or the other but
I don't think people read present tense
and imagine it I don't think people read
past tense and imagine it happening in
the past they just imagine as it's
happening right they both act like
present tense third person or past tense
is just the standard uh and that's what
I use uh for a lot of my books so first
person really good with digging into a
Viewpoint first person can also cheat
see how much time do I have left okay it
can cheat on info dumps which is why I
like to bring this up during the info
dump
discussion if you write a really
interesting narrative in first person
your infodumps become characterization
moments and indeed the best of them are
fun funny and clever and so suddenly it
doesn't matter what the first person
narrator is writing you're there for it
and it can it's kind of the power of
humor to make an info dump uh just go
down easier I mean Douglas Adams coasted
on this I won't say Coast it was very
hard he wrote very well but like Hitcher
Sky of the Galaxy in part works because
he can infodump and have you love it you
don't want him to ever stop info dumping
the your often your favorite parts of
those books are where you're reading a
literal encyclopedia
entry right and they're the most fun um
and that's kind of the the the cheat
code that first person has is you can
info dump a little easier third person
can do this third limited um but
generally in third limited you let the
character's voice color The Narrative
but not completely Infuse it part of the
reason to use third limited is it does
add this sort of moderating force this
um moderating is the wrong term kind of
it Blends all these disparate viewpoints
together and makes them feel like one
complete story when you're writing in
third limited and you write from a
four-year-old's Viewpoint you don't
write like an actual four-year-old would
talk in first person you would and it
would be aggravating right in third
person you let that view of a child
change the sense structure to be simpler
you occasional put occasionally put
interjections that feel very childlike
and they're motiv very childlike but
there's a sense that there even in third
even though it's not omnicient is the
hand of the author there smoothing
things out and making it feel like a
cohesive story even if the viewpoints
are distinctive this is part of why I
think it works very well for large
casts uh just a few other things um
first person Storyteller and epistolary
give away that somebody
survived to at least long enough to get
you that ending now epistolary they can
die halfway through and someone else can
take over and things like that but
particularly this first Storyteller why
I think it moved to this because it used
to be like this you used to all the old
classic books were you know were like
bbo he's telling you the story of his
life but then you know that they surviv
long enough and know the twist that they
were a ghost all along is not new and
original you can still do things that
aren't new and original but it has been
done quite a bit it's like oh it's a
first person narrative haha I did die at
the end and I'm a ghost telling this you
know to people in heaven
um so you can probably think of some
stories that do that um so there is this
sort of inherent firstperson weakness to
this idea that
well I know they live but that's why the
intimate happened the intimate is not
supposed to actually be recorded
anywhere uh and it kind of makes up for
some of those
weaknesses uh often times I can see a
first person where you will have two
different first person viewpoints that
contrast each other a great deal and
those can make for fantastic books if
you do more than two it starts to get
rough everyone's named I and the
transition between them can be really
jarring and it be can be hard to keep
track of so uh those are just a few
things on why you might choose one of is
the other true omnition super hard and
you don't get a lot out of it but it is
it can be really cool um in true
omniscient you generally don't want to
hide things from the reader you want to
give them all the information meaning in
true omniscient you depend on suspense
and not mystery you know who the the
that Dr UA is going to betray them you
are in suspense of what that's going to
do to everyone because as soon as you
see Dr UA you know his motivations what
he's planning to do and what's going on
and that's how a true omniscient
generally Works um so yeah I feel like
obviously in doing that works super
well but what's kind of
like I feel like you just do that
limited too you just have different
chapters what's that like I feel like
you can do that in a limited perspective
have different chapters you can you can
totally do that I'm just saying in
omniscient people will feel you're
cheating if you don't do it does that
make sense um you can go to Storyteller
instead and then the Storyteller can
cheat and they can be mad at the
Storyteller and that works but if you're
true omniscient and they feel the the
the author isn't giving them the
information and limited you get the
choice in omniscient you need to lean on
suspense rather than mystery yeah what
kind of switching between like tenses or
view like like first or third yeah can
you get away with you can get away with
a lot um and it really depends and if
the reader says oh I see why you're
doing this you want them to understand
why for instance I mentioned Name of the
Wind Name of the Wind starts from this
uh Viewpoint of this person who's
collecting trying to find the story of
this great hero from who is now retired
and it starts un limited you get to know
who this guy is he finds the hero who's
washed up as an inkeeper he's like I
need to know your story and how you
ended up as an inkeeper he's like all
right I'm going to tell it to you and
then it switches to first person and
then occasionally you probably it's it's
The Princess Bride structure right oh
yeah name of the wi is Princess Bride
occasionally they
interrupt and you know like is this a
kissing book more it's like
no tell me more about this and it'll
jump into like an interstitial where
you'll be in third limited again and
it'll be in one of the viewpoints of the
characters who's listening to the main
character tell his story and offering
some commentary on it and then he'll
start into it again and then it goes
back into first person that's just one
example you and I showed you um with uh
speed of dark she switches tenses uh you
can do all kinds of things just the
reader has to buy into
it um how about unreliable narrators or
like deliberately Nar yeah yeah
unreliable narrators will generally work
in all of these except for kind of the
true omniscient and it's it's actually
it's it's possible in any of them um so
you just want to approach it differently
so in third limited is the one where
you'll feel like you're cheating the
most okay unless the reader has
significant signifiers that they're
unreliable a classic example of working
really well is is uh Matt from uh The
Wheel of Time where what he says and
thinks is different than what he
does and he consistently does this and
you as a reader pick up on it by Robert
Jordan using just a little bit of
hyperbole in the way Matt thinks to draw
contrast to his actions so you
understand he's unreliable uh where
people will think you're cheating is
like something I flirted with in
mistborn where keler has a secret plan
we've been in as you point a
lot I have to acknowledge he has a
secret plan but I'm not telling you what
it is and so I do the the classic third
limited I can't think about that right
now I've got to be focused it it is a
bend and it feels like a bit of a cheat
every time you do it but it is kind of
the sort of thing you have to do maybe
you can find another way but that's one
of the ways you make that character
unreliable as you let the reader know in
over in this world Storyteller world and
epistolary um and things um even in this
uh true um uh thing you can be truly
unreliable it's harder in that middle
one because you feel like you're with
them in the story all along um and you
can be presenting the wrong
story all along usually in the the true
you want to have those same sort of
limited signifiers that say everything
this character saying may not be true uh
for
instance the Storyteller first person
works very well for this a lot of people
will confront uh Pat rothus about Name
of the Wind oh we're almost out of time
this is May last story and be like uh
this isn't possible and he'll his answer
will be like you thought qu was telling
you the truth about this thing that
would have made him seem really bad if
he hadn't if he told you the truth clo
was lying and indeed he's a very
untrustworthy narrator the more you
indicate that to readers the better
unless you want to have your twist
ending um and then you can kind of pull
off the deck in the face all right guys
thank you um more questions next week
all right